Finding Aid for Little Traverse Conservancy Records, 1972-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Horace M. Huffman, Jr. Files 1972-1994
  - Preserve prospects circa 1982 (Box 3)
  - Preserve reports circa 1982 (Box 3)
  - Publications 1979-1989 (Box 3)
  - Round Lake Preserve 1982 (Box 3)
  - Saur, Charles 1987-1990 (Box 3)
  - Staffing: Bailey correspondence January-March 1986 (Box 3)
  - Strategic Planning 1990 (Box 3)
  - Sturgeon Bay 1981-1983 (Box 3)
  - Stutsmanville Bog undated (Box 3)
  - Swanson correspondence February-March 1982 (Box 3)
  - Tanton, John 1979-1983 (Box 3)
  - Trustee indemnification 1986, undated (Box 3)
  - Verdor property, Roger Smith 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    (includes correspondence to and about Roger Smith, Chairman of General Motors and LTC's fundraising liaison with the University of Michigan)
  - Volunteer questionnaire February 1986 (Box 3)
  - Walloon 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Walloon: Adgate property November-December 1986 (Box 3)
  - Walloon Hills July 1985 (Box 3)
  - Walstrom Marina 1980-1982 (Box 3)
  - Winston, Chuck 1986 (Box 3)
- Projects
  The Projects series (1.3 linear feet) details the major land preservation projects undertaken by LTC (many other minor projects not mentioned in this series are referred to in other series, particularly in the Tom Bailey Files and the Horace M. Huffman, Jr. Files). The subseries are as follows: the Thorne Swift Nature Preserve Project, the North Point Project, and the Colonial Point Forest Project.
  The Thorne Swift Nature Preserve Project subseries spans 1976-1984 and contains documents relating to its establishment and management. Included in the subseries are many newspaper articles and one photograph of a Lake Michigan beach.
  The North Point Project subseries consists of one binder kept by Tom Bailey. Included in the subseries are minutes of the North Point Committee meetings that describe the project's progress, correspondence, and clippings.
  The Colonial Point Forest Project subseries describes one of LTC's largest and most ambitious undertakings and is consequently its most extensively documented project. The subseries is divided into six sub-subseries which roughly represent the major phases of the project. They are Initial stages, Foundations and endowments, Project work, Follow-up activities, Miscellaneous items, and Tom Bailey's Colonial Point files. There are two files entitled "Land Trust Fund," one found within the Initial stages sub-subseries and covering March 1985-August 1986 and the other found in the Foundations sub-subseries and covering May 1985-June 1987. The information is similar in content and some of it is duplicated.
  Some controversy arose while the project was ongoing when an Indian claim to the land surfaced. A legal document dating from 1917 was eventually discovered that was accepted as voiding the claim, however. This topic is dealt with in the Indian title claim files within the Initial stages sub-subseries and the Tom Bailey's Colonial Point files sub-subseries, and also in newspaper clippings and letters found within the General correspondence files of the Project work sub-subseries.
  Of some minor interest in the Follow-up activities sub-subseries is correspondence with Willard Scott of the "Today Show" regarding an invitation for him to conduct a weather report from Colonial Point Forest. In the end he was unable to do so, however.
  The items in the final sub-subseries, Tom Bailey's Colonial Point files, duplicate or supplement the rest of the series and provide a useful "at-a-glance" summary of the project.
  - Thorne Swift Nature Preserve Project
    - Correspondence 1976-1984 (Box 3)
    - Proposals 1981-1984 (Box 3)
    - Articles and press releases 1982-1985 (Box 3)
    - Budgets, contracts and plans circa 1981-1983 (Box 3)
      (includes Nature Center building floor plans and some correspondence relating to the budget)
    - Interpretive displays: general plans, display case plans, photocopies of photos, memos (Box 3)
  - North Point Project 1987-1989
    - Meeting minutes: North Point Committee and North Point Finance Committee (Box 3)
      (includes some letters and memos)
    - Publicity-articles (Box 3)
    - Fundraising plan: plan drafts, Trust Fund application material (Box 3)
    - Natural Resources Trust Fund: plan draft, correspondence (Box 3)
    - Foundations: sample request and thank you letters (Box 3)
    - Financial (Box 3)
      (consists mainly of budgets and donor lists)
    - Miscellaneous items: brochure, presentation to Charlevoix Township Board, correspondence, agendas, and "fact sheets" (Box 3)
  - Colonial Point Forest Project 1984-1987
    - Initial stages
      - Before Devereaux (Box 4)
      - Old title abstract (Box 4)
      - Indian title claim (Box 4)
      - Land Trust Fund March 1985-August 1986 (Box 4)
        (also called the "Michigan Natural Resources Trust Fund")
    - Foundations and endowments
      - Bauervic-Paisley Foundation (Box 4)
      - Colonial Point Endowment Fund [re: Saur Endowment Fund] (Box 4)
      - Frey Foundation (Box 4)
      - Gerstacker Foundation (Box 4)
      - Kennedy Foundation (Box 4)
      - Kresge Foundation (Box 4)
      - Land Trust Fund May 1985-June 1987 (Box 4)
      - Nature Conservancy (Box 4)
      - Offield Foundation (Box 4)
      - Saur Endowment Fund (Box 4)
      - U of M Interest-free loan: University of Michigan (Box 4)
      - Whiting Foundation (Box 4)
      - Other Foundations, rejections (Box 4)
    - Project work
      - Research: research abstract, proposals, correspondence with the University of Michigan Biological Station 1986-1987 (Box 4)
      - Timber appraisal, by Lynn Sandberg Forest Products March 1985 (Box 4)
      - Purchase documents (Box 4)
      - General correspondence, 4 folders
        (includes letters, memoranda, press releases, and newspaper articles)
        - December 1984-February 1985 (Box 4)
        - March-July 1985 (Box 4)
        - August 1985-July 1986 (Box 4)
        - August-April 1989 (Box 4)
    - Follow-up activities
      - "Today Show": correspondence with Willard Scott concerning the possibility of announcing from and about Colonial Point Forest December 1985-April 1986 (Box 4)
      - Colonial Point addition 1993 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous items (Box 4)
        (includes clippings, press releases, an annual report and a dedication packet)
    - Tom Bailey's Colonial Point files
      - Correspondence August-October, 1985 (Box 4)
      - Credit and cash flow: budgets, monthly progress reports, memos October 1985-April 1987 (Box 4)
      - Foundations 1985 (Box 4)
      - Fundraising materials: flyers, articles, 1985(?)-1986 (Box 4)
      - Fundraising plan: reports, charts, drafts, memos June-August 1986 (Box 4)
      - Indian claim: clippings February 1985-May 1986 (Box 4)
      - Land Trust May 1985-September 1986 (Box 4)
        (includes letters of support from State Senator Mitch Irwin and University of Michigan Biological Station director David Gates)
      - University of Michigan: incoming correspondence September 1985-April 1987 (Box 4)
      - Publicity: clippings February 1985-March 1987 (Box 4)
      - Minutes and memos July 1985-July 1987 (Box 4)
      - Background (Box 4)
        (includes copies of certificates of survey, University of Michigan study abstracts (Albert & Miller), press release)
      - Mailings January 1985-September 1986 (Box 4)
- Audio-visual materials
  The Audio-visual materials series (2 DVDs and 1 VHS tape) includes LTC videos "Little Traverse Conservancy" (1995), a 3-segment video program; "Founding Fathers" (2004), and "Protecting Northern Michigan for Generations to Come" (2004).
  - Little Traverse Conservancy 1995 (Box 4)
    (VHS)
  - Founding Fathers 2004 (Box 4)
    (DVD)
  - Protecting Northern Michigan for Generations to Come 2004 (Box 4)
- Executive Director Files (Tom Bailey) 1985-2006
  [RESTRICTED, access to the Tom Bailey Files requires written permission of the donor. Consult the Bentley Library reference archivist for details.]
  The Executive Director Files (Tom Bailey) Files series (4.5 linear feet) is important in supplementing the topical files with more information on the various projects of the LTC. The researcher will find it useful to cross-reference topics referred to elsewhere in the record group with items from the appropriate dates in this series. In addition, the series charts the development of LTC with Bailey at its helm and provide insights into the mind and personality of its longest-serving executive director. The series documents LTC affairs from late 1984 on from its executive director’s perspective. The files are chronological and cover the period from Bailey’s arrival in December 1984 through 2006. From 1984 to 1992, each annual file is divided into general headings of Correspondence, Memos, Meeting Notes, and News releases, with the additional “Activity Reports” in 1988, covering the span of 1986-1988. Items under this level are arranged chronologically. (An exception occurs in 1992, when letters and memoranda are merged into one “Correspondence” file.) From 1993 on, rather than being separated by form, all items are intermixed within one annual file and arranged strictly chronologically, with the addition of a separate “Policy development” file in 1993. The year 1995 saw the addition of e-mail into LTC’s correspondence.
  Included in the Correspondence files are many thank you letters for financial and land donations, along with leads on potential future donors, correspondence regarding projects and other LTC business, and some personal correspondence to friends and family members. The memos provide a clearer picture of project details and an inside look at LTC. Good summaries of LTC activities are provided in the Meeting notes files (which consist mainly of Executive Committee meeting minutes, with some additional handwritten notes) and the News releases files, when available.
  Some important events and topics in LTC history that are referenced in the series include the Indian title claim and other Colonial Point business in 1985 and 1986, the development of a new personnel policy beginning in 1987, the Holnam cement plant deal in January-March of 1991 (and some limited follow-up to it in 1992-1993), a staff development workshop in April 1993, and some follow up on an earlier proposed name change to LTC (see the LTC name change file in the Horace Huffman, Jr. Files series) in November 1995. A topic of interest not discussed elsewhere in the record group includes Tom Bailey’s growing concerns and thoughts about public policy, tax policy, and urban sprawl as expressed in a letter to James Richmond of the Frey Foundation in August 1992. The draft of a moving tribute to Huffy’s memory can be found in a letter of condolence that Bailey wrote to Huffman’s widow, Jane, on December 6, 1996.
  Several instances of LTC’s association with the area’s local Ottawa (Odawa) Indians, the Little Traverse Bay Bands, come up. These include outgoing correspondence to Native American columnist Simon Otto from 1993 through 1996; LTC’s official support of the Little Traverse Bay Bands (LTBB) in the latter’s goal of federal recognition in August 1994; the drafting of policies in September 1994 allowing and regulating the gathering of plants growing on LTC preserves for medicinal and ceremonial use; and Bailey’s efforts, beginning in September 1996, to include a representative of the bands on the LTC Board of Trustees (although some mention had been made to there being an LTBB representative on the board as early as 1995).
  Some topics in the series fall outside of the realm of Tom Bailey’s official role as executive director and represent his private efforts. In September 1995 there is correspondence regarding a recent testimony, in Bailey’s private rather than organizational capacity, before State Senator George McManus’ Senate Select Committee on Public Land Ownership, Purchase and Management, and subsequent correspondence in February 1996. Bailey had, in particular, opposed the raiding of the Natural Resources Trust Fund by the legislature for projects not related to the environment. From March 1995 to June 1996, Bailey was involved, along with Horace M. Huffman, in the bicycle pathway project of the Tri-County Bikeway Committee. From June 1996 to September 1997 Bailey corresponded with the directors and staff of the Holy Childhood Daycare Center, mainly in regard to the forced retirement, to which Bailey was opposed, of the elderly Sisters staffing the center. Throughout the series one will find references to Bailey’s personal convictions, such as his pro-hunting, pro-gun ownership beliefs, as well as his interests, such as his newfound passion for guitar-playing in 1997.
  - 1985
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 5)
      [RESTRICTED]
      (includes December 1984)
    - Memos (Box 5)
    - Meeting notes (Box 5)
    - News releases (Box 5)
  - 1986
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Memos, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Meeting notes (Box 5)
    - News releases (Box 5)
  - 1987
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Memos
      - January-April 1987, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - May-December 1987, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Meeting notes (Box 6)
  - 1988
    - Correspondence, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Memos, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Meeting notes (Box 6)
    - News releases (Box 6)
    - Activity reports: quarterly reports to Trustees 1986-1988 (Box 6)
  - 1989
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Memos (Box 6)
    - Meeting notes (Box 6)
    - News releases (Box 6)
  - 1990
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Memos (Box 6)
    - Meeting notes (Box 6)
  - 1991
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Memos (Box 7)
    - Meeting notes (Box 7)
  - 1992
    - Correspondence: letters and memoranda, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Meeting notes (Box 7)
  - 1993, 6 folders
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 6 folders (Box 7)
    - Policy development 1993 (Box 7)
  - 1994
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - 1995
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - 1996
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - 1997
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - 1998
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - 1999
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - 2000
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - 2000-2001
    - Sale of domain name (Nature.org) to the Nature Conservancy 2001 (Box 8)
  - 2001
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - 2002
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - 2003
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - 2004
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - 2005
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - 2006
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - 2009
    - Correspondence and memoranda (Box 9)
  - 2010
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 2011
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 2 folders (Box 9)
- Tom Bailey: Other activities
  The Tom Bailey: Other activities (1.5 linear feet) series contains more information related to other roles Tom Bailey has played in addition to LTC executive director. This series further illustrates Bailey’s strong commitment to environmental causes and his personal convictions. Roles include chairman of the Emmet County Park and Recreation Committee in 1992 (and vice-chairman in 1991) and chairman of the Emmet County Solid Waste Planning Advisory Committee from 1982 to 1990. These roles and the activities of the committees are documented in those files. Before his arrival at LTC, Bailey was Water Quality Specialist for the DNR and Michigan EPA and as such was involved in a lawsuit in which he cited the Addison Products company for violation of hazardous waste labeling requirements. The case began in 1983 and ended in 1986. Also in the series is the Natural Resources Commission files, which documents Bailey’s efforts, and those of others on his behalf, to obtain an appointment to the Engler Administration’s Natural Resources Commission. He was ultimately successful, being made a member of the Water Resources Commission in July 1993. Other files document his earlier activities as an environmentalist. These include his work with the Michigan Student Environmental Confederation and his support of legislation designating a portion of Isle Royale as a wilderness area. Folders with projects dated after the year 2000 include material on Bailey's involvement with creation of the Heart of the Lakes Center for Land Conservation Policy and the Emmet County Recreation Complex. The series also includes Bailey's published newspaper and journal articles, transcripts of his speeches, material of seminars and presentations given by Bailey, as well as clippings of articles about Bailey and his activities, dated from 1984 to 2012.
  - EPA-Addison Products case: correspondence, hazardous waste reports, legal documents December 1983-October 1986 (Box 9)
  - Natural Resources Commission: correspondence, Tom Bailey's resumes, letters of recommendation September 1987-July 1993 (Box 9)
    (includes correspondence to and from the Engler Administration)
  - Emmet County Park and Recreation Commission 1986-1992
    - Meeting minutes January-June 1992 (Box 9)
    - Publicity: one newspaper article undated (Box 9)
    - Projects
      - General 1989, undated (Box 9)
        (includes correspondence, memos, clippings, and a sample conservation easement)
      - Resort Township: "Emmet County Recreation Plan Supplement: A Study of Resort Township Needs" (Box 9)
      - Cecil Bay: copies of maps, project description, memos and letters, grant application December 1986-February 1992 (Box 9)
      - Camp Petosega: correspondence, project description, copies of maps and photographs, board resolution, and grant application November 1986-June 1992 (Box 9)
      - Spring Lake: map (Box 9)
    - Bylaws 1989-1990 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence December 1989-June 1992 (Box 9)
      (includes Tom Bailey's letter of resignation as commission chairman)
    - Miscellaneous administrative items 1986-1992 (Box 9)
      (includes work plans, insurance survey, planning information on other regional county parks)
  - Emmet County Solid Waste Planning Advisory Committee 1982-1990
    - Organization: member list (Box 9)
    - Minutes March 1988-July 1990 (Box 9)
    - Committee work plan 1987-1988 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence January 1986-January 1991 (Box 9)
      (correspondence includes attachments such as plan drafts and articles)
    - Budgets 1988 (Box 9)
    - Act 641, Rules: Michigan's Solid Waste Management Act 1979-1982 (Box 9)
    - Draft state plan April-June 1988 (Box 9)
    - Emmet County Solid Waste Management Plans 1982-1988 (Box 9)
      (includes a map, plans and plan supplements and a technical bulletin)
  - Michigan Student Environmental Confederation
    - Board of directors meetings and related 1973-1974 (Box 10)
    - Testimonies and other communications regarding Michigan House Bill No. 4881 (establishing wilderness and natural areas) 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Isle Royale wilderness designation 1973-1976
    - Correspondence, testimony, and other materials relating to his support of the proposal (Box 10)
    - House Interior Committee Hearings, testimony and related 1973 (Box 10)
    - Communications and testimony of Bailey and others 1973 (Box 10)
    - Collected material about Isle Royale (Box 10)
    - Citizens alternate proposal for wilderness in Isle Royale National Park 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Isle Royale National Park legislation (Box 10)
    - Windigo Area, Isle Royale National Park 1979 (Box 10)
    - Isle Royal/Grand Portage seasonal employment (Box 10)
    - Olaus Murie-Harvey Broome Award 1973 (Box 10)
  - Michigan Outdoors Habitat Brokerage 1997-2000, 1 volumes; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Michigan Great Lakes Protection Fund, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 10)
  - Water Resources Commission appointment and related 1993 (Box 10)
  - Personal: include thank you letters, etc. (Box 10)
  - Emmet County Recreation Complex 2004-2006 (Box 11)
  - Heart of the Lakes Center for Land Conservation Policy 1992, 2003-2004 (Box 11)
  - Newspaper clippings 1986-2012, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Office of Regulatory Reinvention 2013 (Box 11)
  - Published articles 1984-2012 (Box 11)
  - Speeches, seminars, presentations 1989-2008, 4 folders (Box 11)